James M. Crawford Papers 1906-1988 Mss.Ms.Coll.66
American Philosophical Society
- Series IV. Research Notes, 1962-1988
  - Series IV-D. Research Notes & Notebooks--Other, 1906-1988
    - Newari, 1961
    - Numerals from Indian Languages
    - Ojibwa, n.d.
    - Reconnaissance of Southeastern Indian Languages--Notebook, 1969
    - Shona--Notebook
      - Folder #1, 1973
      - Folder #2, 1974
    - Shoshoni--Notebook (Box Series IVD: Shos - Unidentified--Notebook #7)
      - Folder #1, 1967
      - Folder #2, 1968
    - Shoshoni Notes, 1967
    - Mrs. Terrell--Notebook, 1969
    - Timucua, 1975
    - Unidentified, n.d.
    - Unidentified--Notebook, n.d.
      - Folders #1-7
      - Folder #8 (Box Series IVD: Unidentified--Notebook #8 - Y)
    - Wolof--Notebook
      - Folder #1, 1975-1976
      - Folder #2, 1976
      - Folder #3, 1976-1977
      - Folder #4, 1978
    - Wolof Notes, 1977
    - Wolof Rough Notes, 1976
    - Yavapai Word List, 1962
- Series V. Card Files, 1960s-1980s
  contains card-sized paper slips that are mainly dictionary entries for several languages. The slips have pencilled notes in English and in the languages covered. The various languages include Alabama, Catawba, Choctaw, Cocopa, Mobilian, Newari, Yavapai, and Yuchi. There also three boxes of slips that Crawford apparently did not finish filing before he died, and there are three boxes of miscellaneous slips. The labels on the boxes have been copied from the labels that were given to the boxes by Crawford.
  - English - Alabama (Box Series V: 1)
  - Alabama - English
  - Catawba - English (Box Series V: 2)
  - English - Catawba (Box Series V: 3)
  - Choctaw - English (Box Series V: 4)
  - English - Choctaw (Box Series V: 5)
  - Cocopa - English (Box Series V: 6)
    - a - i
    - k (Box Series V: 7)
    - kw (Box Series V: 8)
    - l - ly (Box Series V: 9)
    - m (Box Series V: 10)
    - n - ny (Box Series V: 11)
    - nyu - p (Box Series V: 12)
    - q - s (Box Series V: 13)
    - š (Box Series V: 14)
    - s (Box Series V: 15)
    - t - w (Box Series V: 16)
    - x (Box Series V: 17)
    - xw - y (Box Series V: 18)
    - ? -?i (Box Series V: 19)
    - ?w (Box Series V: 20)
  - English - Cocopa (Box Series V: 21)
    - A - B
    - D - E (Box Series V: 22)
    - F - G (Box Series V: 23)
    - H - I (Box Series V: 24)
    - J - M (Box Series V: 25)
    - N - Ph (Box Series V: 26)
    - Pi - Py (Box Series V: 27)
    - Q - Sh (Box Series V: 28)
    - Si - Sy (Box Series V: 29)
    - T - Z (Box Series V: 30)
    - A - U (Box Series V: 31)
  - Spanish Loanwords in Cocopa (Box Series V: 32)
  - Kiliwa - English (Box Series V: 33)
  - English - Kiliwa
  - Miscellany #1 (Box Series V: 34)
  - Miscellany #2 (Box Series V: 35)
  - Miscellany #3 (Box Series V: 36)
  - English - Mobilian (Box Series V: 37)
  - Mobilian - English
  - Newari; Unidentified (Box Series V: 38)
  - To Be Filed (Box Series V: 39a)
    - b - h
    - t - y (Box Series V: 39b)
    - y -? (Box Series V: 40)
  - English - Yavapai (Box Series V: 41)
  - Yavapai - English
  - Yuchi - English (Box Series V: 42)
    - b - č
    - čh - dæ (Box Series V: 43)
    - de - (Box Series V: 44)
    - do - gi (Box Series V: 45)
    - go (Box Series V: 46)
    - go - he (Box Series V: 47a)
    - he – h^ (Box Series V: 47b)
    - ž - k (Box Series V: 48)
    - k' (Box Series V: 49)
    - l - l' (Box Series V: 50)
    - l - m (Box Series V: 51)
    - na - no (Box Series V: 52)
    - no - n' (Box Series V: 53)
    - p - p' (Box Series V: 54)
    - d2 - š' (Box Series V: 55)
    - s - s' (Box Series V: 56)
    - š - š' (Box Series V: 57)
    - t - t' (Box Series V: 58)
    - w - w' (Box Series V: 59)
    - y - y' (Box Series V: 60)
    - z (Box Series V: 61)
    - ? (Box Series V: 62)
  - Yuchi Dictionary (Box Series V: 63)
    - A - Z
  - English - Yuchi (Box Series V: 64)
    - A - Be
    - Bi - Cl (Box Series V: 65)
    - Ca - Cy (Box Series V: 66)
    - Co - E (Box Series V: 67)
    - F - G (Box Series V: 68)
    - H - Herd (Box Series V: 69)
    - Here - Hy (Box Series V: 70)
    - I - Im (Box Series V: 71a)
    - In - L (Box Series V: 71b)
    - M (Box Series V: 72)
    - N - Pa (Box Series V: 73a)
    - Pe - R (Box Series V: 73b)
    - S - Sk (Box Series V: 74a)
    - Sl - Te (Box Series V: 74b)
    - Th - Ty (Box Series V: 74c)
    - U - Wh (Box Series V: 75a)
    - Wi - Z (Box Series V: 75b)
    - Dictionary (Box Series V: 76)
- Series VI. Course Material, 1961-1986
  mainly contains course notes for graduate courses in linguistics that Crawford took at the University of California at Berkeley in the 1960s, including Old Church Slavic, Russian, and Sanskrit. There is a photocopied version of a text for a course, Linguistics 888, that Crawford taught, probably at the University of Georgia.
  - American Indian Languages--Linguistics 170, 1962 (Box Series VI: A - I)
  - Cocopa Sketch--Handout for Seminar at University of California at Berkeley, 1963
  - Dravidian Seminar--Linguistics 290H, 1964
  - Indo-European--Linguistics 150, 1962
  - Linguistics, n.d. (Box Series VI: L - R)
  - Linguistics 35, 1963
  - Linguistics 130, 1963
  - Linguistics 140, 1961
  - Linguistics 145, 1963
  - Linguistics 150, 1962
  - Linguistics 220a, n.d.
  - Linguistics 225, 1964
  - Linguistics 290g, 1962
  - Linguistics 888, 1986
  - Old Church Slavic--Notebook, 1962; 3 Folders
  - Russian, 1961
  - Sanskrit, 1961 (Box Series VI: Sa - Se)
  - Seminars: 290a Theory; 290g American Indian Languages; Dialectology 216; 225; 130 Phonology--Notebook
- Series VII. Photographs, 1963-1973
  Native American Images note: Photographs and slides of a Yuman family of the Cocopa tribe that James Mack Crawford met while researching the Cocopa language for his dissertation. Taken by Crawford, the black and white gelatin silver prints show Native Americans from the Somerton reservation that moved to Buckeye, Arizona in 1963. Dressed primarily in modern clothes, some images display women in native neck ware. The 1978 photographs appear in Crawford’s published work, Cocopa Tales (1983).
  - Lillian Hayes and her daughter Mildred, 1963; 1.0 Item(s) 5 x 7 inches gelatin silver print
  - Lillian Hayes and her daughter Mildred, 1963; 5 x 4 inches gelatin silver print
  - Victor Hayes, 1963; 5 x 4 inches gelatin silver print
  - Victor Hayes, 1963; 7 x 5 inches gelatin silver print
  - Mary Thomas, 1963; 7 x 5 inches gelatin silver print
  - Mary Thomas, 1963; 5 x 4 inches gelatin silver print
  - James Mack Crawford, Lillian Hayes, Victor Hayes, 1978; 5 x 7 inches gelatin silver print
  - James Mack Crawford, Lillian Hayes, and Victor Hayes, 1963-1978; 5 x 4 inches gelatin silver print
  - Two daughters of Mary Thomas, Ilona and Vivian, 1963-1978; 5 x 4 inches gelatin silver print
  - Two daughters of Mary Thomas, Ilona and Vivian, 1963-1978; 5 x 4 inches gelatin silver print
  - Two daughters of Mary Thomas, Ilona and Vivian, 1963; 7 x 5 inches gelatin silver print
  - Two daughters of Mary Thomas, Ilona and Vivian, 1963; 10 x 8 inches gelatin silver print
  - Daughters of Mary Thomas, 1963; 5 x 4 inches gelatin silver print
  - Josephine Thomas, 1963-1978; 5 x 4 inches gelatin silver print
  - Josephine Thomas, 1963-1978; 5 x 4 inches gelatin silver print
  - Josephine Thomas, 1963-1978; 5 x 4 inches gelatin silver print
  - Josephine Thomas, 1963; 7 x 5 inches gelatin silver print
  - Josephine Thomas, 1963-1978; 5 x 4 inches gelatin silver print
  - Lillian Hayes and her daughter Mildred, 1963; 2 nitrate negatives
  - Victor Hayes, 1963; 2 nitrate negatives
  - Cocopa texts, 1963-1978; 3 nitrate negatives
  - Lillian Hayes and her daughter Mildred, 1963; 1.0 Item(s) 4 ½ x 4 inches gelatin silver print
  - Victor Hayes, 1963; 4 ½ x 4 inches gelatin silver print
- Series III-A, IV-B (Oversize 1)
  Oversized
  - Series III-A, Works by Crawford--Cocopa
    - Cocopa Dictionary-- Disks (20), [198-]
  - Series IV-B, Research Notes & Notebooks--Yuchi
    - 10 3/4 in. magnetic tape, 30 Oct. 1979
    - 6 in. magnetic tape, 2 Oct. 1985
    - 7 1/4 in. magnetic tape, 12 Dec. 1985
    - 10 3/4 in. magnetic tape, 17 Sep. 1986